Indiana University Office of University Safety records, 1966-1977 C136
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Office of University Safety records
1966-1977
1972-1976
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. Office of University Safety
C136
2.4 cubic feet 3 boxes
Creation of a Safety Department at Indiana University was authorized in 1939. In 1971 the University gained the right to appoint police officers and University Safety became a fully empowered law enforcement agency. A new organizational structure for the Office of University Safety, implemented in 1971 and revised in 1973, included the I.U. Police Academy, which operated a police cadet program. Collection includes annual reports, policy and procedure manuals, training information and correspondence. Most prominent are records related to the police cadet program.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
Creation of a Safety Department was authorized in 1939. Throughout the period following World War II, security functions expanded to meet the needs of a rapidly growing university community. From a staff consisting of one assistant to the Dean of Students in the late 1940's, the Bloomington Safety Division grew to a force of approximately 50 officers in 20 years. The security force at the Indianapolis campus was about the same size by 1970. The other regional campuses had only informal safety or security operations prior to that year. Since the duties of these separate organizations were primarily custodial, it was considered sufficient for them to derive authority as security forces from special police or deputy sheriff commissions.
In 1970, in response to a perceived need for a more sophisticated campus law enforcement agency, the president of the University initiated a plan to reorganize safety operations statewide. In cooperation with other state universities, I.U. prepared H.B. 1358 for consideration by the 1971 Indiana General Assembly. The bill, as amended, was signed into law on March 30, 1971 (I.C. 20-12-3.5-1 et seq.), enabling the Boards of Trustees of the universities concerned to appoint police officers. On April 24, 1971, the Trustees of Indiana University passed a resolution implementing the law that established University Safety as a fully empowered law enforcement agency. The office was given jurisdiction on all regional campuses, with the exception of Fort Wayne, which was within the jurisdiction of Purdue University. A new organizational structure for the Office of University Safety, implemented in 1971 and revised in 1973, included three operational divisions (Bloomington, Indianapolis, and Regional), as well as the I.U. Police Academy, which operated a police cadet program for students.
The Department of University Safety is now known as the Indiana University Police Department. Records in this collection indicate that the terms were used in interchangeably for many years, which caused some confusion for university administrators, faculty, and students. In light of this, "Indiana University Police Department" became the favored term in the mid 1970s, though it is not clear when this change was made official.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into two series: Administrative files and Indiana University Police Academy (I.U.P.A.).
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Office of University Safety span the years 1966-1977 and are organized into two series: Administrative files, and the Indiana University Police Academy (I.U.P.A.).
The first series, Administrative files, spans the years 1966-1977, and contains records and correspondence that document the general activities and policies of the Office of University Safety. This series is organized alphabetically by folder heading and includes annuals reports, training information, policy and procedure manuals, employment information, and various other items.
Indiana University Police Academy (I.U.P.A.), the second series, spans the years 1970-1977 and contains records relating to the administration of the IU Police Academy. Much of the material in this series pertains to the I.U.P.A. Cadet Program and includes brochures and information about recruitment and cadet training. Items related to funding for the I.U.P.A. from the Indiana Criminal Justice Planning Agency (I.J.C.P.A.) represent a large portion of this series. Other items include memoranda, inquiries, and general correspondence.
Separated Material
A small amount of Irvin K. Owen's personal papers have been removed and processed separately as Collection C428.
Related Material
Additional records such as newsletters, annual reports, bulletins, and publications may be accessed in the Archives of Institutional Memory http://institutionalmemory.iu.edu/aim/
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 3036-3037
Provenance
Transferred to the University Archives in 1977.
Campus police --Indiana --History --20th century --Sources.; Police training --Indiana.; Owen, Irvin K. (Irvin Kyle), 1920-; Indiana University Police Academy; Indiana University. Office of University Safety -- Archives; Indiana University. Office of University Safety -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University Police Academy -- Archives; Indiana University Police Academy -- Records and correspondence
- Administrative files, 1966-1977; undated (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
  - Career Information to Applicants of the I.U.P.D., undated (Box 1)
  - Commendations, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Commissioning Ceremony, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Emblem Transparencies, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Five Year Review and Recommendations, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Flyers Mailed, 1971 (Box 1)
  - General Regulations, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - General university announcements and information, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Harvey Report, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Law Enforcement Training Board, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
  - L.E.E.P. Loan Letters, undated (Box 1)
  - Legislation, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Letters of Application, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Management Information Survey, 1972-1976 (Box 1)
  - Manual of Policies and Procedures, 1974; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Manual of Policies and Procedures (Draft), 1974; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Morning Summary, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
  - Oaths, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Office of University Safety, 1971-1976 (Box 1)
  - Operation Theft-Stop, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Pay Classification - Police Officers, 1969-1977 (Box 1)
  - Personnel – Executive Officers, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Policy on Bomb Threats, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Policy on Obscene Telephone Calls, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Private Foundations, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
    - 1973 Proposal, 1971-1973 (Box 1)
    - Ford Foundation, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Lilly Endowment, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Letters of Inquiry, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Proposals, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Duplicates, Miscellaneous, & Original, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Fromm's Draft, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Reorganization of Safety Division, 1969-1976 (Box 2)
    - Resolution, 1971 (Box 2)
    - The Indiana University Plan, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Recommendations for Future Operations of University Safety of Indiana University, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Reorganization, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - Research, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Space, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Statistics, 1966-1972 (Box 2)
  - Study of Safety and Security, undated (Box 2)
  - Summary of Operational Training, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Traffic Conferences - Special Events, 1972-1975 (Box 2)
  - Training, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Training Bulletins, undated (Box 2)
  - University Safety Board, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Veterans Administration, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
- Indiana University Police Academy (I.U.P.A.), 1970-1977; undated (Box 2)
  - Cadet Program (Box 2)
    - Brochures, 1972-1977 (Box 2)
    - Brochures - Mailing List, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
    - Cadet Commendations, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - Cadet Recruitment, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
      - 1974 Recruitment, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - 1975 Recruitment, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976 Recruitment (Box 2)
    - Cadet Schools, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
      - 1974 Schools, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
      - 1975 Schools, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
      - 1976 Schools, 1974-1976 (Box 2)
      - Training, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Certificates, undated (Box 2)
    - Evaluation, 1973 (Box 2)
    - General files, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
      - 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 2)
      - 1974-1975 (Box 2)
        Separated Materials
        Individual cadet evaluations separated and restricted; housed in Box 3.
      - 1975-76 Academy, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - Letters to Applicants, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Questionnaire, 1972-1976 (Box 2)
    - Training Calendar, 1971-1977 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - G.I. & Veteran Inquiries, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
  - Grants, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Indiana Criminal Justice Planning Agency (I.C.J.P.A.), 1971-1975 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 2)
    - Evaluation of the I.U.P.A Cadet Program, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Grants, 1971-1974 (Box 2)
    - Plan (Originals), 1972 (Box 3)
    - Plan (Copies), 1972 (Box 3)
    - Plan Request for 1973, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Proposal and Action Grant, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Quarterly Reports, 1971-1974 (Box 3)
    - Request for funds, 1972 (Box 3)
    - State Plan Request for 1975, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Inquiries, 1974 (Box 3)
  - Instruction Staff Profiles, 1972 (Box 3)
  - J401 Criminal Law Credit, undated (Box 3)
  - LEEP Loans, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
  - Memorandums, 1971-1976 (Box 3)
  - Reunion Questionnaire, 1975-1976 (Box 3)